<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A few words occasioned by a paper lately printed, stiled, A discourse concerning the Quakers. Together with a call to magistrates, ministers, lawyers, and people to repentance. Wherein all men may see, that the doctrine and life of those people whom the world scornefully calls Quakers, is the very doctnrie [sic] and life of Christ. Written for the sake of the simple minded ones, who are willing to follow Christ under the crosse, and to deny all things to be his disciples. By a servant of the Lord, reproached by the world, and carnall worshippers, under the name of a Quaker; whose name in the flesh is Iames Nayler.</title>
            <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89837</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N279</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E731_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202987</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863098</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863098</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115280</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89837)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115280)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 112:E731[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A few words occasioned by a paper lately printed, stiled, A discourse concerning the Quakers. Together with a call to magistrates, ministers, lawyers, and people to repentance. Wherein all men may see, that the doctrine and life of those people whom the world scornefully calls Quakers, is the very doctnrie [sic] and life of Christ. Written for the sake of the simple minded ones, who are willing to follow Christ under the crosse, and to deny all things to be his disciples. By a servant of the Lord, reproached by the world, and carnall worshippers, under the name of a Quaker; whose name in the flesh is Iames Nayler.</title>
                  <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
                  <author>A. P.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to an untraced work attributed to Thomas Ledger in "An answer to (vindicate the cause of the nick-named Quakers of such scandalls and untruths as is falsly cast upon them in a lying pamphlet, otherwise called) A discourse concerning the Quakers" (Wing B1094) by George Baiteman.</note>
                  <note>To the reader signed: A.P.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March. 17. 1654 ["4" crossed out].3".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ledger, Thomas.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115280:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Few Words occaſioned by a Paper late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Printed, Stiled, <hi>A Diſcourſe concerning the</hi> QUAKERS.</p>
            <p>Together with a Call to Magiſtrates, Miniſters, Lawyers, and People to Repentance.</p>
            <p>Wherein all men may ſee, that the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Life of thoſe People whom the world ſcornefully calls <hi>Quakers,</hi> is the very Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctnrie and Life of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Written for the ſake of ſimple minded ones, who are willing to follow Chriſt under the Croſſe, and to deny all things to be his Diſciples.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Servant of the Lord, reproached by the world, and carnall worſhippers, under the Name of a</hi> Quaker; <hi>whoſe Name in the Fleſh is</hi> Iames Nayler.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115280:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MEeting lately with a Printed Paper, ſtiled, <hi>A Diſcourſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Quakers;</hi> and finding many things in it deeply reflecting on the ſpirit of the Lord ſent into the hearts of men to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove and convince them of ſinne, and reproaching his holy people, whom he hath called out of the world; and that it was ſcattered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad into many hands, and ſo might prove a ſtumbling blocke to weake minds: I was moved to ſend it to a friend in the Weſt, who for the ſimple ones ſake, hath given forth a few things, that truth might appeare. And if there be any that by Reading this, ſhall be brought to diſcover truth from error, or to lay to heart their condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and how they have hitherto trifled away their pretious time: There is another Paper now in the Preſſe, from the ſame hand, which will ſhew forth the true light that guides to God, and opens the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, removes the doubts about the great power of the Lord mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in ſhaking the earthly part of thoſe he brings to himſelfe, plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declare the deceipts of the falſe prophets of the world, and let the Magiſtrate ſee the bounds of his Authority. There is another Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per come forth by the Author of the former Diſcourſe occaſioned by ſomething Writ in Anſwer to it, by one who ſaith he is none of thoſe called <hi>Quakers;</hi> and yet the Diſcourſer chargeth all things he ſaith on them. But the Paper ſufficiently bewrayes the Authors weakeneſſe, and its owne folly. Reade without prejudice, that thou may receive Inſtruction, and not increaſe thy owne miſery.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115280:2"/>
            <p>A Paper being come to my hand, which is full of deceit, under pretence of Religion and a Forme of Profeſſion, ſtriking at the life of all Religion, which is obedience to all the commands of God in the ſpirit; and under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the Letter, which he calls the Word, he goes about to reproach, and ſcorne, and ſleight the teachings of Chriſt in the ſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it whereby he rules in the conſciences of his Saints, and by which light he reveales the Father in them, and thereby declares himſelfe to be the Eternall Word, and Witneſſe within his: which Word firſt was known within them, a free gift of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without any Letter, or humane Learning and then decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out in the Letter. But they who (as the Jews) thinke they have ſalvation in the Letter, are enemies and perſecutors of<note place="margin">John 5. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> them who have the Eternall Witneſſe of ſalvation in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:<note place="margin">Gal. 3. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> And from that ſpirit hath this Paper its foundation; for God having put the enmity between the carnall and the ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Seeds there can be no agreement. Now though I abhorre ſtriving for Maſter-hood in words or writing; yet for the ſake of the ſimple ones, who not yet having the true judgement and ſalt in themſelves to diſcerne of ſpirits, are ſubject to take great ſwelling words of mans wiſedome, for the power of God unto<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 5. 6.</note> ſalvation. I am therefore moved to lay open ſome of the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceits in this Paper, that where truth and ſimplicity is in the heart, it may more cleerly judge of truth from dece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t.</p>
            <p>The Paper is Titled, <hi>A Diſcourſe concerning the Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is no new thing for the deareſt ſervants and children of God<note place="margin">Pſal. 69 12.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal 31. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> to be a diſcourſe a reproach, a taunt, and by-word, a wonder and<note place="margin">Pſal. 22 6.</note> a ſcorne to fooles, and wicked men: and to have the belly-god, and drunkard to make ſongs of their ſad and afflicted conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;<note place="margin">Pſal 60 12.</note> and to be called by nick-names, ſuch as it pleaſeth <hi>Iſhmaels</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 10. 20.</note> brood to caſt upon them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to be called <hi>Devills, Deceivers, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, Franticke, Madd men, Quakers,</hi> and ſuch like; but it is,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115280:3"/>
that the ſame Scriptures may be fulfilled in the Saints, that were in Chriſt their example; As they have done unto me, ſo will<note place="margin">Luke 23. 31.</note> they doe unto you; If they keep my ſayings, they will alſo keep yours; If they have called the good man of the houſe <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> how much more them of his houſhold.</p>
            <p>Thou ſayeſt, <hi>Its plainely fore-told, that in the laſt dayes ſhall be the greateſt Deceivers, and worſt of Hypocrites, men extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily inſpired with a ſpirit of lyes and deluſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is above ſixteen hundred yeares ſince thoſe were foretold, and they have had ſo long a time ſince, to broach their deceits<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſtrengthen themſelves in the earth, that the deceit is now growne a monſter, and hath got many heads and hornes; reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions<note place="margin">Revel. 13. 1.</note> and formes one at warre with another, ſtriving with words, and weapons, who ſhould be greateſt. But now that Chriſt is ariſen in his Saints, to reveale this man of ſinne by his<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2. 7. 8.</note> light, and to deſtroy him with the ſword of his mouth. All<note place="margin">Ezek. 38. 18. 19.</note> formes of Religions, the Beaſt and the falſe Prophet, <hi>Gog</hi> and<note place="margin">Acts 4. 26. 27.</note> 
               <hi>Magog,</hi> are joyned together to ſtrike at this light; and no wonder, for that deceitfull ſpirit knowes, that that light which diſcovers him in one forme, will diſcover him in all. And now the Devill would paſſe Judgement upon that light, which is come to judge him where he is, and ſo ſet any whom he can prevaile in, to caſt reproach upon it, under many odious names, that ſo he may keep people at a diſtance from ſo much as own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">Luke 6. 22.</note> it; for he knowes, if any owne it, there he is diſcovered, and diſ-owned; and this is his way in all in whom he ſpeaks, to cry out againſt thoſe that walke in the light in generall, calling them, <hi>Deceivers, Heretickes, Hypocrites, denyers of Scriptures</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 24. 14.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 6. 13. 14.</note> 
               <hi>and Ordinances,</hi> and many ſuch words, as he thinks may make the truth moſt odious to others, but not once ſhew in what par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; ſuch walke contrary to the Scripture, for the deceit knowes that if it come to tryall, it ſelfe will be found that which walkes contrary to the Scripture; for the ſame light that gave out the Scriptures, leades not contrary to it. And now who will be the greateſt deceivers, whether a poore, deſpiſed, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, reproached people, whom God hath called out of the worlds wayes, words workes, worſhip, riches, and pleaſures, and ſo are become ſtrangers and wanderers to and fro, <hi>ſeeking a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115280:3"/>
City whoſe builder and maker is God,</hi> Heb 11. 26. 27. 28. and for this obedience, being counted the <hi>off-ſcouring of the world,</hi> 1 Cor.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 9.</note> 4. 9. 10. 11. 12. 13. and ſuffering all with patience, as the Saints<note place="margin">10, 11, 12, 13.</note> did, who declared this in Scripture; or they who profeſſe that Scripture which witneſſeth theſe things, but ſtill are in their<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 16.</note> luſts, pride, covetouſneſſe, exaltations over others, living like<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. 11. 14.</note> fat Swine in the Earth, differing from the world in nothing, but onely in notions and long Prayers, whereby they appeare to be great deceivers then the world, who profeſſeth nothing but what they are? And for the worſt of Hypocrites, for they who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the higheſt things, and moſt like to Saints, which they live not the life of, nor are ſanctified, as they were, whoſe conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they profeſſe; theſe are the worſt of hypocrites. And for the great traine thou ſpeaks on, would not thou have been as much offended at thoſe many thouſands that followed Chriſt and his<note place="margin">Mat. 14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 21.</note> Diſciples, when they Preached the ſame Goſpel; if thou hadſt lived then, they who were of thy ſpirit, were as much diſquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at it then, as thou art now? Thou ſayeſt, <hi>It hath been an old project of the Devill, to deſtroy the Letter, the ſupreame authority of the Scripture;</hi> Thou art blinde, which ſayeſt that the Letter is the ſupream authority of the Scriptures; for that which gave it forth in parables to the <hi>Serpents Seed,</hi> and opens it againe in<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 14. 26.</note> the <hi>Saints</hi> as they grow in their meaſures<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and opens the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures in and to all, is the ſupreame authority of Scriptures, which is not the <hi>Letter, but the Spirit,</hi> 2 Cor. 3. 6. And they who waite to have the Scriptures fulfilled in them by Chriſt, goe not about to deſtroy the Letter, but to eſtabliſh it. And for the judgements of men thou talkes of, what is their judgements worth, where the practice is wanting, God is not ſerved with words? There are two ſorts of people, which thou conceiveſt to be moſt odious to all people; and thou would ranke theſe whom thou would reproach amongſt either of them; but come to try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and thou wilt finde thy ſelfe farre neerer either of theſe then they. And firſt for Papiſts; which of the Idolatrous worſhipps and traditions of the Papiſts, or that are ordained for Popiſh ends, doe theſe practice? but it may be, thou thy ſelfe art yet in the Idols Temple, builded by the Papiſts for Idolatrous wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, never commanded by God, and for ſuch worſhip is kept up
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115280:4"/>
and uſed at this day; if thou be not yet in many Popiſh Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes as obſerving dayes, and times, and ſeaſons, and perſons,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 10.</note> and outward Traditions of men, not commanded of God which theſe whom thou reproacheſt doe all deny. And the Papiſts are one with thee in reproaching, and ſcorning and perſecuting theſe to their power. And for thoſe thou calleſt <hi>Raunters,</hi> is there any people in the Nation, that more differ in practice then they? and if thou would looke at thy own pride, fulneſſe, and the ſatisfying of thy luſt, thou would ſee little difference between thee and them, but in judgement. And thou art offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at the <hi>knowledge of Chriſt within the Saints;</hi> art not thou aſhamed to profeſſe the Scripture, and deny what they witneſſe? Which of the <hi>Saints</hi> did witneſſe any other knowledge of Chriſt after his Aſcention, but as he was revealed in them? and all that know him in ſpirit, knows him within them; and is there any<note place="margin">Gal. 1. 16.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Coll. 1. 17.</note> Chriſt but one? becauſe thou ſayeſt, <hi>they know no other Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13. 3. 5.</note> 
               <hi>but a Chriſt within them;</hi> and thou that knowes no Chriſt but<note place="margin">Iohn 14. 20. &amp; 15. 4 &amp; 27. 23.</note> without, ye know him not, but by heare-ſay; and then art not thou that Notioniſt thou ſpeakes on. Reade theſe in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent,<note place="margin">Gal. 2. 20. &amp; 4. 19.</note> and ſee who denyes the Scriptures, and the Saints condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions<note place="margin">Ezek. 38. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9. 20. &amp; 12. 18.</note> And thou ſayeſt, <hi>That their quakings are either counterfeit, or comes from the power of the Devill.</hi> How art thou not afraid<note place="margin">Hag. 2. 6 7.</note> to ſpeake againſt the holy Ghoſt? ſearch the Scriptures, and thou<note place="margin">Amos 8. 8. 10.</note> ſhalt finde, that God hath ſaid, <hi>All Fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh ſhall quake and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 110. 24 25.</note> 
               <hi>before him:</hi> and the holy men of God doe witneſſe That the way by whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h they came to know God was <hi>through quak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezra 10, 1</note> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 12. 24.</note> 
               <hi>trembling, faſting and weeping,</hi> which thou that art in the Fleſh, and the earthly part in thee ſtands unſhaken, knowes not, and therefore ſcornes it. But its no new thing for this Generation, to render the works of God, under the name of the Devill Thou ſayeſt, <hi>they will goe in raggs;</hi> doeſt thou now ſpeake truth, how many haſt thou ſeen deny whole cloathes to goe in Raggs; art not thou inſpired with a lying ſpirit thou ſpokeſt on before: but<note place="margin">Iſay 2. 20. &amp; 31. 7.</note> it may be thou art diſpleaſed th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t they pull off their pride, as Gold and Silver: that which they doe in obedience to God, thou would render it onely as a ſhew. But ſee what ſpirit that is thou ſpeakeſt from: And why art thou offended at a meane<note place="margin">Dan. 10. 2. 3.</note> Diet, or <hi>puniſhing the body,</hi> as thou calls it? Did not <hi>Daniel</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115280:4"/>
all pleaſant meats for three full weeks. And <hi>David</hi> afflicted<note place="margin">Pſal. 69. 9. 10.</note> his ſoule through Faſting<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and it turned to his reproach, with ſuch as thou. And why art thou offended, they ſhould care for no more then meat, drink and cloathes, when Chriſt forbids his<note place="margin">Mat. 6. 31, 32, 33, 34.</note> to care for ſo much. And the Apoſtle exhorts, <hi>Having Food and</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Rayment, be therewith content.</hi> And why art thou offended at<note place="margin">Heb. 12. 5.</note> 
               <hi>ſelfe-deniall, and taking up the Croſſe,</hi> to their own luſts. Doth<note place="margin">Luke 9. 32.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.</note> not Chriſt ſay, <hi>He that will be my Diſciple, muſt take up his Croſſe dayly, and follow me.</hi> And had not the Saints, the luſts of the fleſh crucified on the Croſſe? Why wilt thou profeſſe the Scriptures, and not owne the practice of it, but wrangle with them that doe? Thou ſayeſt, <hi>they are above Ordinances<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> above Scriptures, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 2. 20<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>cryes down all as Formes.</hi> But what Ordinance of Chriſt are they above? It is the Traditions and Inventions of men they are above, as thoſe you call Ordinances have been often proved, and will more appeare upon further tryall. And for being above Scripture, if thou wert not blinde, thou might ſee them live in the life of Scripture, in their meaſures, as they did to whom it was given. Thou art offended <hi>that they ſhould owne an infallible</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 12. 8, 20.</note> 
               <hi>light in them,</hi> which the light of Chriſt is, whoſoever hath it.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 15.</note> Now then, that cannot witneſſe an infallible light, how wilt<note place="margin">Iſay 42. 3, 6, 7.</note> thou be a guide to others, and what haſt thou to doe to judge any? But he that hath the light of Chriſt, hath an infallible light, which whoſoever followes, ſhall not walke in darkeneſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. 12, &amp; 1. 9.</note> but ſhall have the light of life; and as this light ariſeth, judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<note place="margin">Pſal. 36, 9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> is brought forth; for all judgement is given unto the<note place="margin">Mat. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5. 13, 14.</note> Sunne; and in that light all his ſee light, and are led into all truth; and this light ſhewes all things in meaſure: and ten<note place="margin">1 Iohn 5, 6, 7.</note> thouſand being gathered by this light, and not runne before it, ſhall be all taught one way, be of one heart, minde, and ſoule; but all who ſtumble at this light, are in darkeneſſe, confuſion, and at a jarre among themſelves. And whereas thou would make people beleeve, that this light they walke by, will not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the light of the word; that is deceit in yee, for it is the word, which is nigh, in the heart, and in the mouth, and doth<note place="margin">Rom. 10. 8.</note> not oppoſe it ſelfe, but is one with Scripture, as all they are who walke in it; onely it oppoſeth all the twinings and wreſting<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> of the Serpent, whereby he would wreſt the Scripture to deceive
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115280:5"/>
with. Thou ſayeſt, <hi>the Saints have a glorious light in them, but</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 18.</note> 
               <hi>imperfect.</hi> Is there any glorious light, but the light of Chriſt, and thou that calls that an imperfect light, art blinde, and not able to judge of light? It is true, the light is but manifeſt in the<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4. 7.</note> creature by degrees, but the leaſt degree is perfect in its mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and being obeyed, will leade to the perfect day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 17. 23.</note> in it ſelfe, and leads up to perfection all that perfectly follow it. And thou that ſo often would put the externall Letter, that had a beginning, in ſtead of Chriſt the Eternall Word, by which<note place="margin">Rom, 2, 29.</note> all things were made, and who dwelleth in the Saints, and liveth in them, and enlightneth them, doth ſufficiently cleare thy ſelfe<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 12. 46.</note> that thou knoweſt him not in thee. And whereas thou talkeſt of trying the light by the Letter, If thou hadſt him who is the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Witneſſe within thy ſelfe, thou wouldſt ſee thou needeſt<note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. 10.</note> not to try the inward ſubſtance, by the outward declaration; the living by the dead. The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>The Word is powerfull, ſharper then a two-edged ſword, &amp;c.</hi> and this thou twines to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ſimple, and ſaith the Scripture is ſo; why wilt thou wreſt the Scripture to thy own deſtruction, thou haſt long had the Bible by thee; but what hath it cut downe, or divided in thee, or hath it diſcerned the thoughts and intents of thy heart, thou and thy ſinns are not yet divided. Thou ſayeſt, <hi>Owles fly the the light<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> but ſee who cannot owne the light, and they are ſuch<note place="margin">Iohn 3. 20. 21.</note> who love the works of the night. And thou that ſpeaks lightly, vildely, or accurſedly of the light of Chriſt in his Saints, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt evill of that thou knoweſt not, and ſhall account for thy<note place="margin">Iude 10.</note> blaſphemy. And thou deceitfull ſpirit, that gathers up the <hi>work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> power of Chriſt in the Saints, and would attribute it to the Letter, art about to make poore ignorant people beleeve, that<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3, 6.</note> the the Letter is the Spirit, and that the Letter is the Word,<note place="margin">Rom. 7, 6. &amp; 2. 29.</note> which is but a declaration of the Word; and it ſelfe ſaith plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Chriſt is the Word;</hi> but the Letter is not Chriſt; and this<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. 14.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 19. 13.</note> would make people beleeve, that he that hath the Letter, hath the Spirit; when both thou, and many more, may have the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and perſecute the ſpirit, and blaſpheme againſt the holy Ghoſt, as was in the Jews, and is at this day. Thou <hi>ſpeakes</hi> of the Word of God, in which Chriſt and the Spirit <hi>ſpeakes,</hi> and thus thou would <hi>make</hi> them who are blinde beleeve it is the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115280:5"/>
and to prove it thou brings theſe Scriptures, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 2. but was that the Letter by which God had ſpoken to them, which he calls <hi>the Sonne of God?</hi> is the Letter the Sunne? And that in the <hi>Revel.</hi> 2. 17. he doth not ſay, Heare what the Letter ſaith, but <hi>Heare what the Spirit ſaith;</hi> or that in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. 17. is it there called, the Sword of the Letter, or <hi>the Sword of the Spirit.</hi> And thou wilt make people beleeve, that God doth all in the hearts of his people by the Letter without. Thou ſayeſt, <hi>by it he ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, enlightens, comforts, ſeales, witneſſeth, teacheth, &amp;c.</hi> which if thou meane the Letter, which thou calleſt the Word, then the<note place="margin">Iude 1.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn 14. 26.</note> Letter it ſelfe ſhall witneſſe againſt thee in all theſe, that it is not<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4. 30.</note> the Letter, but the Spirit that doth all this, where they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 14. 16.</note> Thou ſayeſt, <hi>Without the Word he doth nothing in us, ſpeaks</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4. 10.</note> 
               <hi>nothing in us, in the higheſt revelations; it is the ground of Faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 10.</note> 
               <hi>and without it Faith cannot act, and the Faith hath no bottome but the Word;</hi> which if thou meane the Letter of Scripture; I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, wherein thou ſayeſt <hi>in us,</hi> here thou ſheweſt thy ſelfe a ſtranger to the works, word, revelation and faith that the Saints did witneſſe, as is plaine in the Letter, for they witneſſe the works of God in them in ſpirit, and not in Letter; the word from Gods owne mouth in ſpirit, and revelation in ſpirit, but<note place="margin">Gal. 1. 12.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1. 17.</note> never any in the Letter. And thou art ignorant of <hi>Abrahams</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 3. 6. 7. 9. &amp; 3. 16.</note> Faith, and the ground of it, which had a ground when there was no Letter, and acted when there was no Letter; but they who are of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Seed, witneſſe <hi>Abrahams</hi> Faith grounded on the Promiſed ſeed, which is Chriſt, and is acted in him, and not on the Letter, which works, word, revelation and faith I wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in me in the ſpirit, and not in the Letter, and that faith which is in Chriſt, ſtands not in Volumes. Thou ſayeſt, <hi>this is a more ſure word of Propheſie,</hi> and to prove it, thou quotes, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 19. where the Apoſtle ſpeaks not of the Letter, but of the light of Chriſt ſhining in the darke hearts, to which they were to give heed that by it they might be led to the day, &amp; this is in their hearts, and not in the Letter, which light thou ſcornes, and calls it an <hi>Ignis fatuus,</hi> a ſatannicall fallen light; but thou yet knoweſt not what thou ſpeakeſt, that blaſphemes the true<note place="margin">Iohn 1. 9. &amp; 19.</note> light that is come into the world, and lighteneth every one that comes into the world; yea<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> them which never ſaw Letter, which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115280:6"/>
is the condemnation of thoſe who obey it not, but love their evill deeds. Thou ſets downe many benefits the Saints have in the Word, which is true; but thou that would aſcribe them to the Letter, knoweſt them not, but in the notion. Thou ſayeſt, <hi>that thoſe that have glorioſer diſcoveries, and revelations of Chriſt to boaſt on, then ever any of thoſe men knew; yet doe caſt downe the glory of their light before the Scriptures, and are in ſubjection to Scriptures and Ordinances:</hi> And thou doſt inſtance the <hi>Diſciples who ſaw Chriſt aſcend.</hi> I anſwer, Whether is it a more glorious diſcovery and manifeſtation of Chriſt, to ſee him appearing in them the ſecond time in the ſpirit without ſinne unto ſalvation, or that to ſee him depart in the fleſh, ſeeing Chriſt tells them, <hi>lt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 9. 28.</note> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1. 10.</note> 
               <hi>is neceſſary that he goe away in the Fleſh, that he may come in the Spirit,</hi> thou doſt ſufficiently cleare thy ignorance, meaſuring<note place="margin">Iohn 14. 28.</note> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 8.</note> others who witneſſe him, with thy ſelfe, who knowes no more of him, but what thou haſt found of him in the Letter. And for that ſubjection to the Scripture and Ordinances, and waiting thou ſpeakes on; did they waite in the letter, and in thoſe formes and cuſtomes, and Idols temples that you waite in; they waited together for the appearance of Chriſt in ſpirit, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in that meaſure of ſpirit they had received? Thou goeſt about to make people beleeve, <hi>that the light of Chriſt which is</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 1. 14.</note> 
               <hi>given to enlighten every one that comes into the world, is a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, or fallen light;</hi> but if thou didſt know, owne, and obey it, it would leade thee out of the fall; and for that end art thou and others ſo often checkt and reproved by it: for your pride,<note place="margin">Iohn 8. 12</note> covetouſneſſe, envy, ſcornefulneſſe, and other ſinnes, which though you now diſobey, as a thing too low for your high no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; yet this light ſhall remaine for an eternall witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all that hate and diſobey it. And whereas thou would ſcandall this light, to leade into exorbitances deceit and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages, and many ſuch things, they are falſly caſt upon this light for all theſe are amongſt you who hate the light; but who ſo obeys and loves the light, it diſcovers theſe, and leades all who follow it into one minde heart, and ſoule; and if ten times ten thouſand that are guided by it, yet not a word of diſpute,<note place="margin">Acts 4. 32.</note> but all <hi>ſpeake</hi> the ſame things. And thou calls the Scriptures, <hi>A ſtanding Rule,</hi> but it is not ſo to you, who cannot beleeve that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115280:6"/>
ever it ſhall be fulfilled in you, as it was given out by the holy Ghoſt; neither will you ſo be tryed by it, but you will wreſt and twine it to make it meet your wills, where your profits, pleaſures, and luſt will not ſuffer you to take up the Croſſe, and come up to it: but if it be a <hi>Standing Rule,</hi> let it ſtand as it is, not confounded with the Serpents Wiſedome, and then prove thy ſelfe by it; and thoſe people thou reproaches and miſ-calls, whether thou or they owne it in practice? Thou calls <hi>the Word of God, the Sunne of truth,</hi> and yet thou would make people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it is the Scripture Letter. Is the Letter the Sunne of truth? may not all that looke on yee ſee thee in Babylon? Thou ſayeſt, <hi>How could it be knowne that there is a God, and Chriſt, and holy</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. 6. 7. 8. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Ghoſt, with their works and worſhips?</hi> I anſwer, If thou <hi>know</hi> not<note place="margin">Iohn 4. 22, 23. 24.</note> the Father, Sonne, and Spirit one God, and the way of his worſhip, other wayes then thou haſt found in the Letter, thou<note place="margin">Phil. 3. 3.</note> 
               <hi>knows</hi> but that in letter and notion, which all the <hi>Saints</hi> of God <hi>knew</hi> in ſpirit and power, and thou worſhips in letter and forme thou <hi>knowes</hi> not what, who doth not <hi>know</hi> and worſhip in ſpirit; and herein thou ſhalt have Chriſt, &amp; all the holy men to witnes againſt thee. Thou ſayeſt, <hi>the holy Ghoſt interprets Scripture by Scripture, und reveales Chriſt, the Father, the holy Ghoſt, the ſoules union with them by Scripture.</hi> I anſwer, The holy Ghoſt where he<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 21</note> is needs no Scripture to interpret Scripture by who gave forth<note place="margin">Iohn 14. 26</note> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 10 11.</note> all the Scripture, and opens it againe; for the holy Ghoſt did not give out the Scripture in Parables to its own ſeed, but to the Serpents ſeed; and as that ſpirit ariſeth, it opens and brings<note place="margin">Iohn 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> all that is ſpoken in Scripture to remembrance, and leades into all truth in its meaſure; and when any in whom the ſpirit was, have made uſe of Scripture in ſuch like caſes, it hath not been to open the meaning to themſelves, but to convince others, who had not the ſpirit, or would not owne it. And for ſovles union,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3. 3.</note> which of the Saints had the witneſſe of their ſoules union, to ſeek in the Letter? but he that beleeveth, hath the witneſſe in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe<note place="margin">1 Iohn 5 10.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 16.</note> in ſpirit, and not in the letter; and for trying and judging,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 15.</note> it is not the litterall, but the ſpirituall man that judgeth all things, and no viſible thing can judge him. Thou would have them to ſuſpect this light; thoſe who have no light to walke by but what they by their wiſedome and learning have gathered
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115280:7"/>
out of the letter, have cauſe to ſuſpect it; but they who have the infallible light of Chriſt, by which all is tryed and judged, and diſcerned, and judgement brought forth into victory, in themſelves by it, they have no cauſe to ſuſpect it, but waite to walke in it. Thou art offended, <hi>that they ſhould ſay, they pray</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5. 17.</note> 
               <hi>alwayes, have the Baptiſme of Fire, eate the Fleſh, and drinke the</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 1. 11.</note> 
               <hi>blood of Chriſt, that they were once as others, Hypocrites;</hi> now why<note place="margin">Mat. 3. 11.</note> wilt thou thus wrangle that the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands and promiſes of Chriſt<note place="margin">John 6. 53.</note> ſhould be witneſſed, fulfilled in the Saints now, as they have bin in Scripture witneſſed. Doth not the Apoſtles exhort <hi>to pray al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, without ceaſing;</hi> and are any Baptized into Chriſt, who are not able to witneſſe the Baptiſme of Fire, and the Spirit, without which, Water Baptiſme availes not to ſalvation? And doth not Chriſt plainely ſay, <hi>that whoſoever eats not his Fleſh, and drinkes not his blood, hath no life in them.</hi> And have not the Saints<note place="margin">Rom. 6. 21.</note> witneſſed a time wherein they were hypocrites, and in the world without the true God. And thou ſayeſt, <hi>they can give no Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture account of the eſtate they are now in,</hi> and yet doſt blame them for owning the Scripture fulfilled in them in theſe things; but that nature could never be ſatisfied with Chriſt, nor any of his, nor any account from them; though they could not convince them of ſinne, yet they would tempt, hate, and perſecute, even till death, if they had power. Thou would make people beleeve, <hi>that theſe deny the rule of the Goſpel, and the divine inſpiring of the holy Ghoſt, the infallible rule of all obedience and worſhip, and judgement of all actions;</hi> but come to tryall and ſee, whether they that owne the light of Chriſt in ſpirit, and follow it; or they that call it an <hi>Ignis fatuus,</hi> deny the rule of the Goſpel? And whether they that witneſſe the ſame ſpirit, and the inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<note place="margin">Rom. 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5, 6, 7, 9.</note> of it, without humane helps, letter or learning, as the<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4. to the 14. verſe.</note> Saints in all ages have done<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> every one in their meaſures of that free gift given to profit withall; or they that would make people beleeve, that all ſuch divine inſpirations and gifts of the ſpirit were now ceaſed, and now the letter is all the ſpirit they muſt look for, deny the devine inſpirations of the holy Ghoſt, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible rule of all obedience and worſhip, and judge of all actions; and for the denying of O dinances, thou ſo much char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth<note place="margin">Mat. 15. 9.</note> them with, if it come to tryall, they will be found onely
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115280:7"/>
to deny your tradition, temples, and humane inventions, never commanded by Chriſt, nor practiſed by any that ever he ſent, and Chriſt never annexed the promiſe of his preſence to that<note place="margin">Rom. 6. 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 7. 18. 22.</note> which he never commanded. Thou art offended, <hi>that they ſhould be ſet free from, or have ſinne taken away from them:</hi> Now thou<note place="margin">1 Iohn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 8. 9. 10.</note> ſheweſt plainely whoſe Kingdome thou wouldeſt uphold: And thou ſayeſt, <hi>that by denying ſinne to be in them they overthrow re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance;</hi> but here thou ſheweſt thy blindneſſe For he that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſakes his ſinne, doth eſtabliſh his repentance; but he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes unto ſinne againe, overthrowes it. Thou tells <hi>of being</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>godded with God,</hi> but ſee what ſpirit that is that thou art led by,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7. 10.</note> who dare take the holy name of God ſo ſcornefully in thy mouth, to caſt as a deriſion upon others. Thou art offended, <hi>that</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 14</note> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 11. 12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>thoſe ſhould witneſſe perfection;</hi> And is it not the end for which Chriſt came into the world, ſuffered<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſent out his Miniſters into<note place="margin">Col. 1. 28.</note> the world? And why doſt thou profeſſe Chriſt, and the Scripture, and thus oppoſes the end of his comming? and what he did worke in his Saints, which is to ſet free from ſinne, and bring<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 10.</note> to perfection, which Chriſt commands, and which the Scriptures witneſſe in the Saints? but there is nothing more oppoſed by<note place="margin">Iohn 17<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 23.</note> the Devill, and his Inſtruments, then to have the worke of mans Redemption perfected. Thou ſayeſt, <hi>the many ridiculous practiſes of their franticke mould, be too much to relate,</hi> And hereby thou wouldeſt render them as vile as thou canſt to others; but the wayes of Chriſt were no worſe, for ſuch as thou ſaying he was mad; for the wayes of God have alwayes been counted madneſſe and folly to that generation: what thou intend in that word <hi>many,</hi> I know not; for where nothing is mentioned in particular, I cannot anſwer. But for thoſe thou nameſt are theſe, <hi>they will not put off the Hat to any, not to a Magiſtrate. That they thinke it a ſpeciall Badge of their profeſſion to ſay and write</hi> Thou <hi>and</hi> Thee, <hi>and by no means ſay Sir or Maſter to any, and that ſome will not anſwer, or ſpeake to any queſtion</hi> and thou quarrells at ſome <hi>for forſaking the world, and giving over their Callings.</hi> I anſwer, When wilt thou ceaſe wrangling at their obedience of the commands of Chriſt witneſſed in the Scripture? Haſt thou nothing amongſt all thoſe many ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous practiſes thou tells on<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to charge on them, but are accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115280:8"/>
to Scripture? Where doth God require putting off Hats, or<note place="margin">Mat. 4. 10.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Iam 2, 1. 9.</note> worſhipping any creature, Magiſtrate, or others? And why may<note place="margin">Pſal. 40, 4.</note> it not be a badge, if thou ſo call it of their profeſſion, to uſe the<note place="margin">Iob 13. 10</note> the Scripture Language? and where doſt thou finde any other<note place="margin">Iohn 5, 44.</note> Language in the Scripture, but <hi>thou</hi> or <hi>thee,</hi> to a particular, whatſoever he was that was ſpoken to? And no wonder that thou ſtumble, that any ſhould witneſſe the power of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, when its taken for ſuch an offence with thee, to witneſſe the outward Language, which all holy men of God have uſed in Scripture; and yet thou calls the Scripture a <hi>ſtanding Rule;</hi> but thou wilt neither make it thy Rule, nor ſuffer them that would. And for refuſing calling Maſter, is it not the command of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mat. 23. 7, 8, 10.</note> and doſt thou deſerve the name of a Chriſtian, who would make it an offence to obey his commands, becauſe it croſſeth thy pride? And for their ſilence, <hi>Is there not a time to ſpeake, and a</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 3, 7.</note> 
               <hi>time to be ſilent?</hi> And <hi>was not Chriſt asked many queſtions, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 27, 12.</note> 
               <hi>anſwered nothing?</hi> And doth not the Scripture ſay, <hi>Anſwer not a Foole according to his folly?</hi> And when Chriſt did anſwer the tempters, it was either with ſilence, or contrary to what they<note place="margin">Luke 14. 26.</note> would have had: And for <hi>for forſaking the world,</hi> muſt not all that will come to Chriſt <hi>forſake the World?</hi> And were they not in<note place="margin">Mat. 10, 37.</note> their Calling, who left their Ships, their Fathers, and receit of Cuſtome, and Wife, and Children, and Lands, to follow the commands of Chriſt? Oh thou enemy of all obedience to Chriſt, doſt thou reproach that which thy carnall heart will not ſuffer thee to follow? thou ſhalt ſinde it true, that whoſoever will not forſake theſe for Chriſts ſake, cannot be his Diſciple; but it ſeems, the neerer to Chriſt that any comes in obedience, the greater is thy malice to ſuch, thou ſhoweſt thy generation. And art thou not aſhamed when thou haſt done, to charge theſe with diſclayming Scripture-light; thou loves to talke of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, but art an enemy to the walking in them. Thou ſayeſt, <hi>of thoſe uncleane birds, thou haſt heard of none that have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to the Arke;</hi> by which, if thou meane your Temples, or carnall Ordinances, I tell thee, they make a bad returne, who have knowne the Lord in ſpirit, and worſhipped in ſpirit, if they returne into Formes and Cuſtomes againe, to be made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. Thou ſayeſt, <hi>ſeperate not betweene Word and Spirit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115280:8"/>
Graces and Ordinances;</hi> but the Apoſtle doth deny the<note place="margin">Gal. 3. 3.</note> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3, 6</note> miniſtration of the Letter, and ownes the Spirit. And he that cannot diſtinguiſh between the graces of Gods ſpirit, and your outward Formes you call Ordinances<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he knowes but little yet as he ought to know. Thou tells <hi>of Praying and Mourning for ſinne, bewayling the Heart, Reading the Word, and Meditating in it Night and Day:</hi> And thou ſayeſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Its impoſſible for ſuch an one to fall into this condemnation of the Devill;</hi> but I tell thee, though theſe may be done, and in as much zeale as the Phariſees did them; yet if there be pride, envy covetouſneſſe, ſelfe love, exaltation, ſlandering, falſe-accuſing, deceit, diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and hypocriſie, and ſuch like<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which are the workes of the Devill: all thy outward pretences ſhall not keep thee from the condemnation of the Devill, for it is that which leades out of the works of the Devill, that brings from under the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Devill. Thou puts much upon Church-Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but fee if thou be diſtinguiſhed from the world, otherwiſe then in notion, and thy owne conceit, which will deceive thee, and all the covetous oppreſſors in the world in the day of try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. Therefore prove thy ſelfe if thou be a Saint, ſanctified<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">Iude 1.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn 17. 9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 14.</note> come out of the worlds pleaſures, riches, wayes and worſhips, and faſhions, as they were whoſe conditions thou talkeſt on, or elſe thy crying, <hi>the Temple of the Lord,</hi> will but ſtand thee in little ſtead; which if thou deale plainely in, and let truth ſpeak in thee, thou wilt ſee a great diſtance between a Saints life and thine, as between a Saints ſpirit, and thine, which is plainely diſcovered. Thou ſayeſt, <hi>It is obſervable, that where Churches are, theſe Owles dare not appeare:</hi> Theſe reproachfull names be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeems that ſpirit from whence they come; but which of them have refuſed to come, where they have been ſent, for feare of your Churches; or what corners are they in, except it be ſuch as you have ſhut up in priſons or dungeons; doe not theſe that are at liberty meet in the middeſt of common Streets and Fields, where God calls them; and many of the moſt conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious of your Churches owne them, and frequents their mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings; others, who have the feare of God before them, dare not perſecute them in word or deed: but the day is come, that all ſpirits muſt ſhew themſelves. Thou adviſeſt to doe all <hi>according
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115280:9"/>
to Scripture;</hi> it is good advice, but doſt thou that teacheſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note place="margin">Mat. 7. 12.</note>, teach thy ſelfe? doſt thou as thou would be done by in all things? doſt thou forſake pride, and covetouſneſſe, which is Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, and not to be ſo much as named among Saints? doſt not thou ſeek great things for thy ſelfe; having food and rayment,<note place="margin">Jere. 45. 5.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Iam: 4, 4.</note> art thou therewith content? art thou out of love with the world, which is enmity with God? doſt thou not take thought for to morrow, for food and rayment? haſt thou crucified the fleſh, with the affections and luſts, and put off the body of ſin? art thou not a ſcorner, reviler, and falſe accuſer? doſt thou feed the hungry, cloathe the naked, and let the oppreſſed goe free?<note place="margin">Iam. 1 27,</note> haſt thou forſaken all to follow Chriſt? art thou hated of all<note place="margin">Mat. 15. 10. 11.</note> men for the name of Chriſt? haſt thou denied to be called Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter? art thou come to yea and nay in thy common occaſions?<note place="margin">Mat. 23, 8. 10.</note> doſt thou love the Brethren with the ſame love Chriſt hath loved his withall? art thou ſet free from thy ſinne, and raſh paſſions?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5, 37</note> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6, 18.</note> doſt thou hold thy Faith in a pure Conſcience, voyd of offence<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1, 5, 19.</note> towards God and Man? doſt thou walke as Chriſt walked? And many other the commands of God ſet down in Scripture, in<note place="margin">Acts 24, 16.</note> which the Saints walked, as is plaine in Scripture, which if thou<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 2, 6.</note> 
               <hi>walke</hi> iu, there thou doſt all according to the Scripture; but if thou take but ſome part of Scripture to performe as it is given out by the holy Ghoſt, <hi>to wit,</hi> that which will moſt fit thy forme and pleaſe thy owne will, and not croſſe thy luſts, profits and greatneſſe in the world; and for the reſt, either let them ſtand by, or wreſt them by ſubtill meaning and expoſition, to bring<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3. 16.</note> them to bend to thy diſobedient minde; ſhall not God find <hi>thee</hi> out, and plague thee for thy adding and diminiſhing, altering<note place="margin">Rev. 22. 18.</note> and changing that, which was perfectly given forth, to be read and fulfilled as it is? And whereas thou would charge the light of Chriſt ſhining into the Conſcience, which teacheth into oneneſſe, to be the cauſe of all the errors in the world; It is falſe, for the light of Chriſt is but one, and all that are led by<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 14</note> it, walke after Chriſt as he walked; but the cauſe of all errors comes from the Serpents ſubtill twining and wreſting the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, every one for their owne Formes, ends, and carnall tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions; but none of them will owne it to live the life of it as it is, and ſo have it fulfilled in them, as is was in thoſe that ſpoke
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115280:9"/>
it forth. Thou ſayeſt, <hi>Be ſure the Chriſt, the Faith, the Hope, the Baptiſme, the Worſhip, be that which is in Scripture.</hi> Now that Chriſt which the ſaints witneſſed in Scripture, is the light of the<note place="margin">Iohn 8. 12.</note> world, given to enlighten the Gentiles, and lighteneth every<note place="margin">Iohn 1. 9.</note> one that commeth into the world; which light is in the ſaints;<note place="margin">Iohn 1. 7.</note> and whoſoever walkes in it, hath fellowſhip with God, and one with another, and thereby are cleanſed from all ſin, in which light all Sriptures were ſpoken forth; which light thou denyes to be equall with the Scripture, but ſcornes and reproaches with nick-names, as <hi>Ignis fatuus,</hi> a naturall light, making it plainely appeare, that thou art one of thoſe the Scriptures ſpeaks on, <hi>who hates the light.</hi> And the Scripture Faith is that, by which<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 3 20.</note> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. 4, 5.</note> the ſaints overcame the world, ſinn, and the Devill, and gets victory; which Faith, thou in this Paper, canſt not owne, but denyes, and would reproach in them, in whom it hath over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſinne, and brought up to perfection; and he that hath the <hi>Scripture hope, purifies himſelfe, even as he is pure:</hi> and the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme<note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 3.</note> of Chriſt, <hi>is with the holy Ghoſt, and with Fire,</hi> which thou<note place="margin">Mat. 3, 11</note> in thy Paper ſpeaks ſcornefully of in others that owne it. And the <hi>Scriptures-worſhip</hi> is not in Idolls Temples, Formes and Letters; <hi>but in ſpirit and in truth;</hi> and God ſeeks ſuch to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 4, 24.</note> him. And thou ranks up a number of <hi>Raunters, Notioniſts, Papiſts,</hi> and ſuch like, that are moſt odious to people, and with theſe thou puts in thoſe called <hi>Quakers,</hi> and tells of their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions; but thoſe thou ſo calleſt, denies all opinions, and lives in the light and practice of Scriptures; but thou, when thou art proved, will be found more in opinion, then practice: And thou that denies the infallible ſpirit to be in thee, art but in opinions at the beſt. And for the <hi>Purgatory</hi> thou ſpeakes on, thou that ſayes, <hi>None can ever be perfected, and ſet free from ſinne while they are here,</hi> had need to own a Purgatory; but they who are Redeemed, and ſet free from ſinne by the Lambe of God, need it not, but have received the earneſt of their eternall inheritance. And for the word <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> which is but Water<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 21.</note> without, but not that of the ſpirit, the anſwer of a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>and obſerving of Holy dayes;</hi> Firſt cleare thy ſelfe, and then finde fault with them that deſerves. Thou talkeſt of <hi>pittying, and praying for theſe;</hi> but the ſpirit of ſcorning, ſlandering, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115280:10"/>
and the ſpirit of pitty and Prayer, cannot ſtand in one; and where the firſt is, I cannot owne the latter. Thou ſayeſt, <hi>Prayſe the Lord, that hath delivered out of the ſnares of Sathan.</hi> And it<note place="margin">Iam. 3. 11.</note> is true, they who are ſo, can delight in nothing elſe but Prayſes; but whileſt thou commit ſinne, thou art in his ſnares and a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to him. Thou ſayeſt, <hi>Worke out your ſalvation with feare</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 9.</note> 
               <hi>and trembling,</hi> but ſcornes <hi>quaking,</hi> and ſayes, <hi>It is from the power of the Devill;</hi> but it is in this, as in all thy Paper; thou wilt owne the Scripture in notion and letter, but ſcornes and perſecutes the power and practice of it. And now friend, a word to thy preſent condition, as thou art revealed; thou art in the world, in thy fleſhly will, pride of heart, and raſh anger, exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted above thy brethren, and the ſpirit of perſecution acts in thee; thou denyeſt to walke anſwerable to a light in thy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which would leade thee out of theſe things, up into obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, love and meekneſſe; and thy love to the deeds of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, makes thee hate the light: I ſpeake to that in thy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which ſhall eternally witneſſe me at the great day of the Lord, when all ſecrets ſhall be layd open, where thou ſhalt account for all thy hard ſpeeches, againſt the ſpirit of God in his people. Wherefore repent, and take heed how thou ſpeakeſt evill of the things thou knoweſt not, or oppoſeth the ſpirituall Kingdome of Chriſt in the Conſciences of his owne poore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed little Flocke; but turne in thy high minde, and ſee what thou haſt been doing, and who thou ſtriveſt againſt; If he fall upon thee, he will grinde thee to powder, let not thy high mind ſcorne that, which may be for thy eternall good. Search the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and ſee if any of the holy men of God ever acted ſuch things: Now thou haſt time, priſe it, leaſt thou harden thy ſelfe againſt God, and ſo be for deſtruction eternally; thou knoweſt not what ſpirit thou art of: Thy Name I know not, but where thou liveſt I know; and what ſpirit acts in thee, Oh that thou kneweſt in this thy day, the things that belong to thy Eternall Peace.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>My Name in the Fleſh. James Nayler.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:115280:10"/>
            <head>A Call to Magiſtrates, Miniſters, Lawyers, and People to Repentance.</head>
            <p>O Man and Woman, how art thou fallen from thy Maker,<note place="margin">Gen. 1. 26. 27.</note> and from the eſtate wherein thou was created? And how doſt thou lye in the loſſe, and in the fall? How long will it be ere thou enquire after the Lord, who is holy and pure? And you people of <hi>England,</hi> How long will it be ere you leave off your out-ſide formall cuſtomary worſhips, and ſeeke the Lord in truth of heart, bringing forth fruits of righteouſneſſe and<note place="margin">Rom. 1. 2. 3.</note> holineſſe, according to what you profeſſe, that the Lord, who hates diſſembling, may be honoured, not in words, but in life, power, and practice? Doth not your actions declare againſt you before men and Angels, that you are out of the way, and in the<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 28.</note> curſe, Children of the night, and brings forth the fruits of darkeneſſe, and death, and not unto God? And you who ſay,<note place="margin">Iſay 56. 10 11.</note> you are the Teachers of the Nation, How long will it be ere<note place="margin">Jer. 6. 13. 14.</note> you <hi>looke</hi> at your owne wayes? Is not all manner of filthineſſe<note place="margin">Exod. 3. 4.</note> amongſt you, which you ſhould leade the people out of? Is there not among you Drunkenneſſe, Gluttony, Whoredome, and Sporting, ſitting downe to Eate and to Drinke, and riſing up to play; Swearing, Lying, Backbiting, falſe accuſing, Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Slandering, Contention, Strife and Envy? Yea, Are not the beſt of you given to Pride and Covetouſneſſe, which is Idolatry; fulneſſe of Bread, and abundance of Idleneſſe? Are not you Hirelings, and Teach for the Fleece? Doe not you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for Money with your owne Hearers, and ſue them at Law for it; yea, although they cannot ſatisfie your demands, but ſinne againſt the light in their owne Conſcience, and ſo ſinne<note place="margin">Iſay 9. 15. 16.</note> againſt God? Are you not Bitter, and Perſecuters of any that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115280:11"/>
comes to diſcover your lewdneſſe, crying out to the Magiſtrate<note place="margin">Exod. 18. 21. 22.</note> to uphold you in your beaſtly wayes, and to ſtop the mouthes of all thoſe, whom God hath ſent to witneſſe againſt you? And<note place="margin">Rom. 13. 3. 4.</note> much more works of this nature is amongſt you, which the pure<note place="margin">Micha 3. 11.</note> All-ſeeing God, hath ſhewed unto his people to be amongſt you, and therefore it is that they come out from you, leaſt they<note place="margin">Prov. 21. 3.</note> partake with you of your ſinnes and plagues. But are not you blinde, leaders of the blinde, when you neither ſee theſe to be the <hi>workes of darkeneſſe,</hi> nor thoſe that follow you. Woe unto<note place="margin">Iſay 1. 23. 24.</note> you that devoure ſoules for Money and Gaine, The day of your Account is at hand. O repent, the blood of ſoules is upon you.<note place="margin">Jer. 5. 28. 29.</note> Die ever God ſend forth ſuch a Generation of Teachers amongſt his People, who are not taught themſelves by him to forſake<note place="margin">Iſay 3. 14.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Iames 1. 2. 8. 9.</note> ſuch wayes as theſe which you <hi>walke</hi> in? How are you enſam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to the People to follow? The Leader of this People hath cauſed them to erre, and they that are led by them are deſtroyed; and hereby Prieſt and People are at a diſtance from the Lord.<note place="margin">Job. 13. 10.</note> O you Rulers of the People, who are ſet up to judge betwixt a Man and his Neighbour, ought not you to judge for God, and<note place="margin">Luke 20. 21.</note> not for Man? Ought you not to be Men fearing God, and hating Covetouſneſſe, not judging for gifts and rewards?<note place="margin">Prov. 28. 21.</note> Ought not you to countenance and encourage them that doe<note place="margin">Exod. 18. 22.</note> well, and be a terror to them which doe evill; Juſtice is ſo. And<note place="margin">Rom. 13. 3. 4. 5.</note> he that is of God, and beares his Sword, turnes the edge of it againſt all ſinne and wickedneſſe, injuſtice and oppreſſion, and ſo ſets up juſtice and judgement in the gates, that the poore<note place="margin">Prov. 29. 2. 14.</note> may be delivered from him that is to mighty for him, and that the cauſe of the Fatherleſſe, Widdow and Stranger may not fall, but hath an eare open to the cryes of the poore and helpleſſe,<note place="margin">Prov. 10. 6.</note> who hath but little Money and few friends, that a poore man may not be afrayd to appeare in a good cauſe, againſt the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt<note place="margin">Iſay 5. 4. 7.</note> oppreſſor in the Nation. And ought not you to judge with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect to perſons, or without ſeeking reſpect to your own Perſons, Worſhip or Honour from men, but onely to advance<note place="margin">James<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. 9.</note> Juſtice, Equity and Righteouſneſſe which is of God, that ſo you may be honoured by the Lord; for true Humility is Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,<note place="margin">Prov. 15. 33.</note> and he that Honours the Lord, him will he Honour; and ſuch have been honoured in all Ages, though they never ſought
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115280:11"/>
it from men. And when juſtice beares rule, the Righteous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce,<note place="margin">Prov. 22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and the Land is in peace; and wickedneſſe is made to bluſh, and be aſhamed, and the wicked is ſcattered from about ſuch Rulers. O you that Rule in the Nation, Is it ſo? Nay, Is it not quite contrary? O what a height is iniquity growne unto? Doth not all manner of ſinne abound even in open ſtreets; as<note place="margin">Iſay 2. 11.</note> ſwearing, drunkenneſſe, covetouſneſſe, and oppreſſion? Can you paſſe on the ſtreets, and not heare the cryes of it? and although there have been Lawes for reſtraining of ſome of thoſe abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations; yet, how are they ſleighted, ſo that poore People get not the benefit by them? Nay, is it not too plain, that they who ſhould reſtraine others, are many of them guilty of the ſame themſelves: Shall not the Lord viſit for theſe things? The cryes<note place="margin">Iſay 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 28. 29.</note> of the poore oppreſſed ones, is come before the Lord, and he is riſen to avenge him, of him that is too ſtrong for him. O when will you ſee? Hath not want of Juſtice caſt Kings from<note place="margin">1 Chron. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 21. 22.</note> their Thrones, and overturned Nations? And is not the Lord <hi>Overturning, overturning, overturning?</hi> O returne to the Lord, and have a care to uſe your power ſo, as to make a way for pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and holineſſe, that the Kingdome of Chriſt may be ſet up, and Reigne; and that the Seed of God may have free liberty to come out of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> to ſerve the Lord, without feare of Man, out of all Formes, and Cuſtomes, and Magician Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, into the power of purity, and of the ſpirit. Ceaſe from Perſecuting, and Impriſoning the Innocent for crying out againſt the abhominations of the Times, and letting the guilty goe free, leaſt the decree goe forth againſt you, and the wrath<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 4. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> of God burne like Fire, and there be none to quench it. Hath God put Power into your Hands, to oppoſe his owne worke? And you lofty ones of the Earth, who have gotten much of the creation into your hands, and have thereby ſet your Neſts on high, and are become Lords over your Brethren Was the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures<note place="margin">Pſal. 62. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 10.</note> made for that end, to ſet your hearts upon them; to heape together<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> out of the reach of the poore and needy; and he who can get the greateſt ſhare, ſhould become the greateſt man; and all that have little, ſhall bow downe and worſhip him, and ſo breake the command of God, which ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not bow</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exad. 20. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>downe nor worſhip any Creature in Heaven or in Earth.</hi> Are you
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115280:12"/>
not fallen from the eſtate wherein you was Created? for it was not ſo from the beginning; for he who made all things good,<note place="margin">Gen. 1. 31.</note> made all men of one mold, and one blood, to dwell on the face of the Earth; and gave them power over the worke of his hands, not to heape them together, to ſet your hearts upon them; but to<note place="margin">Gen. 1, 26.</note> uſe them to his ſervice, who made all things for himſelfe, and the<note place="margin">Prov. 16. 4.</note> wicked for the day of evill. You that live in your pride, paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your ſelves in your coſtly Apparrell, in venting new wayes<note place="margin">Iſay 28. 1.</note> and faſhions, to make you ſeem glorious in the carnall eyes of others, that they may worſhip you; for this is that which the<note place="margin">Gal. 4. 8.</note> Heathen worſhip, who know not God; and this is that you<note place="margin">Acts 17. 23.</note> 
               <hi>looke</hi> for, which Angels dare not take to themſelves; But <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-like,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſther 3. 5,</note> you rage if you have it not, and beare an evill eye to them, who cannot give that to you, which belongs to God<note place="margin">Iſay 2. 18</note> alone. But the hand of the Lord ſhall be upon all the Idolls of the world; you have forgot that you were but duſt, and<note place="margin">Pſal. 7. 5.</note> muſt to duſt, and God will honour himſelfe in laying all Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours<note place="margin">Iohn 5. 44.</note> in the duſt, which men ſeek to themſelves, and is not of God alone. You luſtfull ones, which lives of the fat of the<note place="margin">Ezek. 34. 3</note> Earth, whoſe care is onely to ſatisfie the Fleſh, and the Luſts thereof, your curious deviſed diſhes, <hi>Dives-like;</hi> Is this the end<note place="margin">Nehe. 8. 10.</note> for which you was made? you are fitted for deſtruction, your day is comming, the cry of your iniquity is gone up before the Lord; the cryes of the poore which you have oppreſſed,<note place="margin">Iames 5. 4. 5.</note> whoſe labours you have ſpent upon your luſts, the Ruſt of your Gold and Silver doth witneſſe againſt you. Repent, repent, caſt off your gorgious Apparrell, and guird you with mourning; Let your Songs of Muſicke be turned into howling; your Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queting<note place="margin">Amos 8. 3. 10.</note> and Feaſting, into Faſting, for the Lord is wrath with you, and the Fire is begun allready. Breake off your ſinnes by Repentance, and your iniquities by ſhewing mercy unto the poore; and turne to the <hi>Lord</hi> with all your heart, from all your evill doings, if ſo be that you may finde mercy; that you may be hid in the day of his fierce wrath, which is to come upon<note place="margin">Zeph. 2, 3.</note> all the workers of iniquity: For he will bring downe the Mighty from their Seates, that he may exalt them of low de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. O take heed how you contend with him; Did ever any doe it and proſper? Shall the Clay ſtrive with the Potter? If<note place="margin">Ier. 1 8, 6.</note>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115280:12"/>
he fall upon you, he will breake you to powder. And you Lawyers, ought not you to pleade the cauſe of equity, between man and man for equity ſake, without reſpect to your ſelves or others, but onely to truth it ſelfe, that a juſt Cauſe may be owned in whom ever it concernes? But is not the juſteſt Cauſe ſure to fall, if the Party have not Money to ſatisfie your<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6, 10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> demands, which are many times very unreaſonable; and you who ſhould inſtruct people in the wayes of truth and peace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Doe not you by your wiſedome teach them lyes, and ſtrife? Doe not you adviſe your Plantives, as you call them, to declare in Bills, things that are not true, and make ſmall offences ſeem very great by falſe gloſſes? For ſay you, <hi>We may Declare what we will, and Prove what we can,</hi> ſo that you and they who you act for, <hi>knowes</hi> before-hand that ſcarce one thing of ten can<note place="margin">Luke 11. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; 52.</note> be proved, neither is true? Is this the way to <hi>make up the breach, and preſerve peace and truth amongſt people?</hi> O miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fall from God, when that Law which ſhould before preſerve in peace, is uſed to aggravate offences beyond truth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo <hi>make</hi> differences greater. And doe not you delight to fiſh in troubled waters? and the greater diſcention amongſt the people, the more is your gaine. Is not your Purſes filled, and your<note place="margin">Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 18. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Eſtates rayſed in the ruings of the People? And are not thoſe<note place="margin">Mal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> Lawes which ought to be uſed to preſerve People from Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, by abuſing, made the undoing of whole Families, impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Townes, and Countries? The Law, as it is now uſed, is ſcarce ſerviceable for any other end, but for the <hi>Envious Man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> who hath much money to revenge himſelfe of his poore Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, which may be never did him wrong. Is there any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing for the poore againſt the rich, although his cauſe be juſt, but by deceit, delayes, and expences, the remedy is worſe then the diſeaſe; ſo that they are made to ſighe and groane under op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion,<note place="margin">Iſay 5, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and their cryes are come into the eares of the juſt God, who is now ariſing to avenge them. And now, Woe to you that ſeem to be eaſers of peoples burdens, but <hi>make</hi> their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions<note place="margin">Iames 5, 4.</note> greater even grievous to be borne; and by increaſing of contentions, have taken away the Key of Knowledge: For what Knowledge hath the <hi>workers of iniquity, who devoure the poore to ſatisfie their owne luſts?</hi> the woe is upon you, for the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115280:13"/>
juſt God <hi>hath ſhaken his hand at your diſhoneſt gaine; Woe unto</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hab. 2, 9.</note> 
               <hi>him that coveteth with an evill covetouſneſſe to his houſe, that he may ſet his Neſt on high. Woe unto him that builds his houſe by oppreſſion and eſtabliſheth the City with iniquity; how are you gone</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier, 22, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.</note> 
               <hi>out of the right way? and how is the cauſe of the poor bought and ſold for money?</hi> Was you thus made at the firſt? are you not in the inventions? is this the end for which we came into the world? are you not in the Earth, and in the Fall, and in the curſe, and at a diſtance from the pure God, who is holy and juſt, and loves Righteouſneſſe? How long will it be ere you will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire<note place="margin">Eze. 18. 30</note> after the right way, or loathe your ſelves for your filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? O Repent, <hi>Returne to the Lord from whence you are falne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 2, 5.</note> 
               <hi>for what will you doe in the end thereof?</hi> Shall not Juſtice from on high take hold on you, who have ſlighted juſtice upon earth? Your day is at hand; <hi>Shall not the Judge of all the Earth doe right?</hi> Why will you deſtroy your ſoules for money? and what will you give in exchange for your ſoules? or ſhall all your gain redeeme you? Doe you act according to the Law of God, which ſayth, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelfe?</hi> Doe not you<note place="margin">Mat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 19, 16,</note> prize the accurſed things, before the love of God, or your Neighbour? Let your practice witneſſe. And you People of the Nation, that have ſeen the hand of God againſt the Prince and People for theſe and the like abominations, and you your<note place="margin">Iude 23,</note> ſelves are eſcaped, as Brands plucked out of the Fire; have you<note place="margin">Zach. 3, 2.</note> at all turned to him who hath ſmitten you? or are you bettered by correction, or have you made your peace with the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? Although you have ſeen warre, and the Sword reaching to the very ſoule, are you not every one, to your owne Power, gathering fuell to that Fire, which hath been burning in the Land, and hath conſumed thouſands, which ſhould have been<note place="margin">Hoſ. 14. 1. 2.</note> as a warning unto you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who are eſcaped, to returne to the Lord from the evill of your doings; But are not you ſtill making the breach ſtill wider between God and the Nation, as though you were left for no other end, but to fill up the meaſure of iniquity that is yet behinde, that the juſt God may ſweepe the Land with the Beeſome of deſtruction? O when will you ceaſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the Lord by your ſinnes? Where is your Redeemer, you<note place="margin">Iſay 14. 23</note> have profeſſed ſo long in words and Formes? Can you witneſſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115280:13"/>
him in your works<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and what hath he redeemed you from? For ſaith he, <hi>Why call you me Lord, and doe not the things which I ſay?</hi> Is he your<note place="margin">Luke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 49.</note> Lord, and you ſervants to all manner of filthineſſe? And notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that you have ſeen his wonders in the Nation, yet doe not you exceed all that ever went before you, in Pride, Covetouſneſſe, Drunkennſſe, Swearing, Envying, Quarrelling, Backbiting, Slande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, falſe accuſing, ſelfe love, and deceit in all manner of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe,<note place="margin">Micha 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and trading; falſe weights and meaſures, ſayings, prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings one towards another; in your bargaining ſpeaking, things that are not true, and hereby to over-reach your brethren, and get diſhoneſt gaine. How many falſe oathes, and idle words are ſpent about every bargaine in your Markets, and open Streets, without bluſhing, or being aſhamed? yea<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it is able to breake the hearts of<note place="margin">Pſal, 31. 17.</note> any, who knowes the pure God, to know it and heare it; For it is come to ſuch height of deceit, that none can truſt his brother; for lying, ſwearing, and for-ſwearing, it abounds in the Nation; And yet you will profeſſe your ſelves to be the Members of Jeſus Chriſt: And had Jeſus Chriſt ever ſuch a body as this? nay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all that are<note place="margin">Phil. 1, 27.</note> Members of him are of one heart, and one ſoule. And you talke of a communion of Saints; Had ever the Saints ſuch a communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note place="margin">Ier. 32, 29.</note> as this, to defraud one another for money; and profeſſe a Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and are ſervants to the Devill, and your owne luſts, in all the motions and temptations thereof, and are led captive at his will? But what redemption is this you witneſſe, ſo long as ſinne is the partition wall, between God and you, ſtands ſtill whole in your wils, you be drunke, ſweare, lye, and commit adultery, diſſemble,<note place="margin">Rev. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 27.</note> and ſatisfie your luſts in all things; and ſay we are redeemed to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit all theſe abominations, and live in them under a pretence of a profeſſion, and going to the Idols Temple once a weeke: Did ever Jeſus Chriſt redeeme ſuch a people, or dwell in ſuch a people? Thoſe whom he hath redeemed, he hath freed from the ſervitude of ſinne, by ſeparating them from ſinne, and reconciling them to God, from whence they are fallen by ſinne; for God and ſinne cannot dwell in one: And to ſuch he ſaith, <hi>Be ye holy, for I am holy;</hi> And as he<note place="margin">John 1. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> is the <hi>Lambe of God who taketh away the ſinnes of the world:</hi> Now ſee, how is your ſins taken away, when the Kingdome of darkeneſſe doth wholly rule in you, and leades you into workes and wayes of darkeneſſe? Are you reconciled to God, and have you fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115280:14"/>
with him? Are not you yet ſtrangers to him, and worſhip an unknowne God? <hi>For he that commits ſinne, hath not ſeen him, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Iohn 3. 6.</note> 
               <hi>knowne him,</hi> and ſo worſhip they know not what, in formall and ſuperſtitious worſhips. O blinde People, who <hi>have eyes, and ſee not,</hi> How long will it be ere you turne your eyes within, and<note place="margin">Pſalme 115. 5.</note> look into your owne ſtanding, or rather into your fall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and how you ſighe under the curſes and wrath of the Almighty? and how farre you are from purity and holineſſe, and that eſtate wherein<note place="margin">Gen. 1. 27.</note> that you was made in the Image of God; and waite to ſee that renewed in you, and you brought up out of the fall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and a ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to be one with God and Chriſt, that you may know what you worſhip, and finde acceptance? But are you not ſo farre from that, that if the Image of God ſeem to be renewed in any, and they begin to turne from theſe, and the like abominations, to ſerve the living God in purity and holineſſe; and they refuſe to partake with you in your Pride, Covetouſneſſe, Drunkenneſſe, and exceſſe<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4. 3. 4.</note> of Ryot, and deny your vaine Heatheniſh Cuſtomes, Faſhions, and Worſhips; and are not ſuch objects of your envy and hatred? and are they not abuſed by you, buffeted, ſcorned, mocked, ſtoped, and called moſt reproachfull names, even in Wayes and Markets, and in your Streets, when you meet with them, though they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſpeake word to you, but beare your reproaches with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? So that he that departs from Iniquity, makes himſelfe a<note place="margin">Iſay 59. 15.</note> Pray to this Generation. Doe not you plainely ſhew forth the Serpents Seed in you, which is at enmity with the Seed of God, where ever it is brought forth; and ſo you ſhew your ſelves to be acted by the Devill who was a Murderer from the beginning?<note place="margin">Iohn 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.</note> And when the judgements, and wrath of God appeares in the Land, Is it not becauſe of your Iniquiries? Doe not you like wicked <hi>Ahab,</hi> charge an innocent People, who cannot partake with you in your wickedneſſe; declaring, that thoſe who are harmeleſſe, to be cauſe of troubles in the Nation, and ſay, They are about to rayſe a new Warre; but never looke at your owne abominations, for which the Land mournes, and the wrath of God<note place="margin">Hoſ. 4. 3.</note> is againſt it, ready to deſtroy it, but ſtill hearden your hearts in your wickedneſſe? And as though all this were too little, have you not added this wickedneſſe now, that God in mercy hath called ſome out of all theſe evill wayes, and ſent them to declare
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115280:14"/>
againſt theſe abominations which the world lives in, both Prieſts and People, not onely in word, but in life and practice, and hath<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 4. 5. &amp; 16.</note> given his power to goe along with them: and are not theſe called by you Devills, Witches, Sorcerers, Conjurers, Jeſuites, and the like<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Are they not ſome beaten, ſome ſtoned, others ſhamefully entreated and Impriſoned? Are they not brought before Rulers, and Governors, for the confeſſing the name of Chriſt? and all this you doe unto them, not for any evill you can charge upon them; but for the name of Chriſt, and his power that goes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with them, in <hi>ſhaking</hi> downe the Kingdome of the Serpent, and bringing his elect out of all the Heatheniſh Cuſtomes and<note place="margin">Iohn 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 23. 24.</note> Worſhips, to Worſhip God in Spirit, and him onely, and not men, nor the Idolls of the World. And now, are you not blinde, who have profeſſed the Scriptures ſo long, and cannot ſee them fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led now in this Generation? Are not thoſe of the ſame brood who called the good man of the houſe <hi>Beelzebub?</hi> and how can they<note place="margin">Mat. 10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 25.</note> doe leſſe to them of his houſhold? Doe not this Generation beate ſome, ſtone and ſhamefully entreat others, that beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the Heire? And hath not Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Yee ſhall be hated</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 22.</note> 
               <hi>of all men for my Names ſake. They ſhall ſpeake all manner of evill of you falſely;</hi> They ſhall ſeperate out of your company, reproach you, and caſt out your name as evill; and you ſhall be brought before Rulers, for a teſtimony againſt them, and for my names ſake: And the Devill ſhall caſt ſome of you into Priſon, that you<note place="margin">Rev. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 10.</note> may be tryed; and you ſhall have tribulations ten dayes: yea, the time comes, that they that Kill you, ſhall thinke they doe God<note place="margin">Mat. 24. 9.</note> ſervice: and theſe things will they doe unto you, becauſe they know not the Father, nor the Sonne: And the Scriptures muſt be fulfilled; and thoſe who have Eyes to ſee, may ſee them now fulfilled, and fulfilling, and they who ſee it, have ſhare in it, and rejoyce, and witneſſe God faithfull, and his Word; but wicked men, and perſecuters, have been blinde in all Ages; For<note place="margin">2 Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 4. 4.</note> the God of this world have blinded their Eyes, and hath thereby made them fit for his owne worke; and his worke is to oppoſe the Lord in all things. Now, all People, ſee where you are, and<note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> what you are doing; where you live, and whom you ſerve; for if you live to the Fleſh, you cannot pleaſe God, for as alwayes,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115280:15"/>
he that is borne after the Fleſh, perſecuted him that was borne<note place="margin">Gal. 4. 29.</note> after the Spirit; even ſo it is now. O be no longer deceived: ſee whether ye be in the firſt Birth, or Borne againe: That which<note place="margin">Iohn 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> is of the firſt is of the Earth, Earthly, and minds Earthly things, feeds upon Duſt; and this is the Serpents Seed: and here are all your envious, haters, perſecuters, covetous, ſcoffers, and ſuch<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3. 3.</note> like; and here will you be found, your actions witneſſe it, you cannot deceive God; you are under the Curſe, and they be the<note place="margin">1 Iohn 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> curſed fruits you bring forth, and they are for the Fire. But the ſecond brings forth no ſuch fruit, for he that is Borne againe, is Borne of the Spirit, and brings forth fruits of the Spirit: he is<note place="margin">1 Iohn 4. 7.</note> Borne of God, and brings forth fruits unto God; fruits of love, meekneſſe, gentleneſſe, patience, temperance, and ſuch like: there was never a Perſecuter of this Birth, for they are called out of all occaſions of ſtrife, contention, and perſecution; for that is all about things of this world, and Formes, and Cuſtomes, that<note place="margin">Ier. 10, 3.</note> periſh. But they who are brought into the ſubſtance, cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend about ſhaddowes; for there, all Diſputes, and vaine jang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 18.</note> ceaſe; For as they are ruled by one Spirit, ſo they are led by one Spirit, into one God, where God, Chriſt, and the Saints are one eternally: but this godlineſſe is a Myſtery to all the World. Now try your ſelves, for by your fruits you are knowne, and ſhall be judged; wherefore all People, looke within, and judge your ſelves, reforme the inſide, looking without to be ſeen of men keeps you Hypocrites, and you have your reward: But<note place="margin">Col. 2. 11.</note> the true Seed of the Jewes, who are of the Circumciſion, made without hands, in the Heart, and ſuch ſeek not prayſe of Men,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Iohn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 3. &amp; 6. 7.</note> but of God; neither are they knowne of men, nor owned of Men, nor have fellowſhip with men; but are rayſed up out of the fall to God, to live with him in joy, and peace, and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, which men talkes of who lives in the fleſh, and in the<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> fall, who are not reconciled to God; and there can be no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation to God, while ſinne ſtands, which made the firſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration: O People be not deceived.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
